Guide to the Bob Sheldon Papers, 1968-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Bob Sheldon papers 1968-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Sheldon, Bob.
2.1 Linear Feet 500 Items
Political activist; nurse; owner of Internationalist Book Store in Chapel Hill, N.C. Sheldon was murdered in the store on February 21, 1991.
Drafts of Sheldon's speeches, articles, diary and notes; news clippings; printed materials; and transcripts of trials and FBI files. Materials relate chiefly to his political activism as a draft resister in 1968; a visit to China in the 1970s, including slides; work with the Communist Workers Party in the 1970s and the Green Party in the 1980s; union organizing at Cone Mills Textile plant in the 1970s; and various Palestine issues in the 1980s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bob Sheldon Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Political activist; nurse; owner of Internationalist Book Store in Chapel Hill, N.C. Sheldon was originally from Colorado, and moved to Chapel Hill in the late 1970s. He opened the Internationalist Book Store as a reading room in 1981, and moved it to a storefront in 1984. The store provided a space for activists as well as a dissemination point for Marxist and other political literature. With the launch of the Gulf War in 1991, Sheldon was interviewed on local television stations as Internationalist Book Store volunteers organized opposition to the war. Shortly afterward, Sheldon was murdered in the store on February 21, 1991. His murder remains unsolved.
Collection Overview
Drafts of Sheldon's speeches, articles, diary and notes; news clippings; printed materials; and transcripts of trials and FBI files. Materials relate chiefly to his political activism as a draft resister in 1968; a visit to China in the 1970s, including slides; work with the Communist Workers Party in the 1970s and the Green Party in the 1980s; union organizing at Cone Mills Textile plant in the 1970s; and various Palestine issues in the 1980s.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Sheldon, Bob
Internationalist Book Store (Chapel Hill, N.C.)
Cone Mills Corporation
Communist Workers Party (U.S.)
Political activists -- Papers of
Booksellers and bookselling
Draft resisters -- United States
Radicalism -- United States
Social change -- United States
Green Party
Textile industry -- North Carolina
Textile workers -- Labor unions
Industries -- North Carolina
Chapel Hill (N.C.)
North Carolina -- Politics and government
China -- Politics and government -- 1949-
Palestine -- Politics and government -- 1948-
Diaries
Slides
Contents of Collection
- Bob Sheldon Papers, 1968-1991, (2 boxes)
  - Political Activism in the U.S.
    - Internationalist Books Resource Center: articles and management, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
    - Annotations on articles and events of political activism, undated
    - Publications and correspondence about the Green Party and political issues, 1986-1988
    - FBI files, 1969-1986
    - Anti-war protest/arrest, 1969
    - Cone Mills Union organizing, 1978, (2 folders)
    - Civil Suit: RCA Plant Strike, 1974
    - Warren County Public Health, undated, (2 folders)
    - Mayday arrest and status reports, 1982-1985
    - American Civil Liberties Union lawsuit, 1989-1990
  - Middle East
    - Iranian Revolution: "The Need for Revolutionary Support of Iranian People's Struggle," undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous articles on Middle Eastern conflict, 1987-1990
    - Resource articles and manuscripts on Palestine, 1987-1989, (3 folders)
    - Clippings on the Middle East, 1988
    - Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) clippings and notes, 1982 and undated
  - China
    - Revolutionary Communist Party notes and China diary, undated (Box 1)
    - Notes on Chinese history, 1979
    - China trip, 1975-1976
    - Public Health in China talk, 1976
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous speeches and writings, 1988 and undated
    - Bob Sheldon's bar mitzvah, and miscellaneous notes and photographs, undated
    - Newspaper and magazine articles about Bob Sheldon's death, 1991
  - Slides
    - Public Health in China talk (March 1976 trip to China) (Box 2)
      Subjects include industry, medicine, people, education, museums, history, parks, scenery, Old China, and miscellaneous.